Guide to the Winterhouse Art and Design Collection of Pentagram Ephemera
Yale University Arts Library
Winterhouse Art and Design collection of Pentagram ephemera
1977-2012
1990-2000
ART 19
Yale University Arts Library
1.25
(1 box)
The collection consists of a variety of pamphlets, booklets, and other ephemera designed by Pentagram.
Drenttel, William, 1953-2013
Helfand, Jessica, 1960-
Pentagram Design
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William Drenttel and Jessica Helfand, 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of a variety of pamphlets, booklets, and other ephemeral publications designed and produced by Pentagram (or Pentagram partners).
Biographical / Historical
Pentagram is an independent design firm owned and operated by 19 partners. Their offices are located in London, New York, San Francisco, Berlin, and Austin. The firm's projects include architecture, interiors, products, identities, publications, posters, books, exhibitions, websites, and digital installations.
Reference: http://www.pentagram.com/
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Pentagram Papers, 1975-2012. II. Pentagram Projects. III. Pentagram Designers' Catalogues. IV. Pentagram Holiday Greetings, 1977-2008. V. Pentagram and Partners Miscellany, 1986-2000.
Commercial art; Design; Pentagram Design
- Pentagram Papers, 1975-2012; Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically according to the sequential numbering. The set is incomplete.
  Scope and Contents
  Pentagram Papers is a series privately published by the Pentagram firm since 1975.
  - Pentagram Papers 1: ABC A Dictionary of Graphic Cliches, [1975]; 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    The folder also includes an article about the Pentagram Papers series by Kathleen Reinmann and published in I.D. Magazine, April 2001.
  - Pentagram Papers 3: Brushes and Brooms, [1976] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Pentagram Papers 4: Face to Face, [1977] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Pentagram Papers 12: Olivier Mourgue's Little Theatre of Design, [1985] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Pentagram Papers 13: Imprimeries Clandestines, [1986] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Pentagram Papers 14: Stars & Stripes, [1987]; 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Pentagram Papers 15: Through the Window, [1985] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Pentagram Papers 16: Kingswalden Notes, [1989] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Pentagram Papers 17: The Many Faces of Mao, [1989] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Pentagram Papers 18: Skeleton Closet, [1990]; 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Pentagram Papers 19: Purple, White and Green, [1992] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Pentagram Papers 20: Architecture, [1993] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Pentagram Papers 21: Crop Circles, [1993] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Pentagram Papers 22: Architectural Toys, [1995]; 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Pentagram Papers 23: Cigar Papers, [1995] (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Pentagram Papers 24: The Arms of Paris, [1996]; 2 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Pentagram Papers 25: Souvenir Albums, [1996]; 2 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Pentagram Papers 26: On Pride and Prejudice on the Arts, [1997] (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Pentagram Papers 26: Nifty Places: The Australian Rural Mailbox, [1998] (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Pentagram Papers 28: Of Money and the Divine, [2000]; 2 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Pentagram Papers 29: Savoy Lights, [2000] (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Pentagram Papers 30: Learning from Wildwood, New Jersey, [2001] (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Pentagram Papers 31: Hinagata; Kimono Pattern Books, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Pentagram Papers 41: WTC, [2011] (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Pentagram Papers 42: Cowboy Poetry, [2012] (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Pentagram Projects, Series II
  This series contains small-format books and ephemera published by the Pentagram firm. The publications reproduce examples of Pentagram design work and are organized by type of project.
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Pentagram Architecture, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Pentagram Identities, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Pentagram Identities, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Pentagram Marks, undated; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Pentagram Marks, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Pentagram: Marks; 400 Symbols and Logotypes, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Pentagram Packaging, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Pentagram Signs, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Pentagram Designers' Catalogues, Series III
  This series contains ephemera that highlight specific Pentagram designers. Each catalogue reproduces examples of the designer's work and provides brief biographical information.
  Arranged alphabetically by designer's last name.
  - Apicella, Lorenzo, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Brunner, Robert, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - The Product Designs of Kenneth Grange of Pentagram, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Greiman, April, undated; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Each pamphlet also includes a computer disc with motion graphics.
  - Gutiérrez, Fernando, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Hyland, Angus, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Miller, J. Abbott, undated; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Opara, Eddie, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Stout, D. J., undated; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Pentagram Holiday Greetings, 1977-2008; Series IV
  Arranged chronologically by date of publication.
  This series contains booklets published by the Pentagram firm as holiday greetings.
  - Cocktails, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Six Domino Puzzles, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Mnemonics, [1990] (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Mystery Objects, [1991] (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - L'Enfance De La Cuisine, [1992] (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Illustrations by Eve Chwast. Printed by Ascensius Press.
  - First Draw Your Circle, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - How Good is Your Taste?, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - The Press-Man's Hat, [1995] (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Six Tunes for Eight Wine Bottles, [1996]; 2 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - A L for Bet, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Ladle Rat Rotten Hut, [1998] (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Story by H. L. Chase. Printed by The Stinehour Press.
  - Crossword, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - All the King's Horses, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Why Do You Say That?, [2001] (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Fitting Words, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Alpha to Zulu, [2005] (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - The Alphabet: A Critical Assessment, [2006] (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Decipher, [2007] (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - A Number of Numbers, [2008]; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Pentagram and Partners Miscellany, 1986-2000; Series V
  - "Battle of Britain Monument", 1987; Crosby, Theo; Guedes, Pedro; Sandle, Michael, 1936- (Box 1, Folder 62)
    Design by Pentagram.
  - "A Child's Treasury of Smart-Ass Remarks", 1992; Gilbert Paper (Box 1, Folder 63)
    Design by Michael Bierut / Pentagram.
  - "Childhood Fantasies", 1991; Champion Papers (Box 1, Folder 64)
    Design by Pentagram, New York.
  - "A Guide to the New York City Design Scene", undated; Steelcase Inc. (Box 1, Folder 65)
    Drawings by Mel Calman. Design by Pentagram.
  - "In the Long Run…", undated; Harold Burch Design (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - "K9", 1986; Pirtle Design (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - "Let's Build a Monument", 1987; Crosby, Theo (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - "Stripes & Stars: A Graphic History of an American Icon", 2000; Hinrichs, Kit (Box 1, Folder 69)
    Catalog for exhibition hosted at AIGA National Design Center. Design by Pentagram Design.
  - "Twenty-Six Letters by Twelve Characters", 1995; Champion Papers; 2 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    Includes contributions by Michael Bierut, Paula Scher, and Woody Pirtle. Portfolio of cards represents silkscreened posters from the International Design Conference in Aspen, June 1995.